A Guide to the Records of the Policy Office of Governor James S. Gilmore, 1998-2001
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Policy Office of Governor James S. Gilmore, 1998-2001
The Library of Virginia
40168
14 cu. ft. (15 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to architectural and engineering plans and drawings of current governmental buildings requires a written request from the prospective user and written authorization from the appropriate authority with the agency occupying the facility.
Access to privacy protected records including but not limited to: prisoner medical records, juvenile criminal records, and criminal records is restricted (public access and photoduplication) for 75 years after date of creation per Code of Virginia 42.1-78.
Records protected by attorney-client privilege and executive privilege are restricted until 2015 January 1 per section 4B of the 2002 November 18 agreement between the Library of Virginia and Governor James S. Gilmore.
Acquisition Information
James S. Gilmore, Richmond, Virginia, accession 40168, transferred on 17 November 2002.
Biographical Information
James Stuart Gilmore III was elected Virginia's 68th Governor in November 1997 and served in this capacity from January 1998 to January 2002. Jim Gilmore was born in Richmond, Virginia, on October 6, 1949. He graduated from the University of Virginia in 1971 with a degree in Foreign Policy and then joined the U.S. Army, where he then graduated with honors from the Army Intelligence School. He joined the 650th Military Intelligence Group and was stationed in West Germany. After his tour was completed, he entered law school at the University of Virginia and graduated in 1977. Jim Gilmore was elected in 1987 as Commonwealth's Attorney for Henrico County, was reelected in 1991 and was elected Virginia's Attorney General in 1993. He is married to the former Roxane Gatling of Suffolk.
Scope and Content
The Records of the Policy Office of Governor James S. Gilmore are housed in 15 boxes. The collection is arranged into twelve series. Series have been designated for: I. Secretary of Administration; II. Secretary of Commerce and Trade; III. Secretary of Education; IV. Secretary of Finance; V. Secretary of Health and Human Resources; VI. Secretary of Natural Resources; VII. Secretary of Public Safety; VIII. Secretary of Technology; IX. Secretary of Transportation; X. Miscellaneous; XI. Records of Lee E. Goodman; and XII. Policy Analysis.
This is an artificial collection compiled by Governor James S. Gilmore. In the 2002 November 18 agreement between former Governor Gilmore and the Library of Virginia, Governor Gilmore agreed to transfer 25 boxes of Policy Files from the Policy Office. While these records were called "policy files" by Governor Gilmore's representatives, the majority of these documents were not actually created by the Policy Office. Most of the records within this series are copies of documents created by Governor Gilmore's cabinet secretaries and the state agencies under their control. In the summer of 2001, John A. Mahone, Deputy Chief of Staff for Operations, apparently requested each cabinet secretary to gather documents for the Governor's personal files documenting the administration's achievements. (For examples of responses to this request see Box 1, Folder 30; Box 3, Folder 32; Box 5, Folder 21 and Box 6, Folder 9) This series represents those collected documents. Also interfiled with this material are a few of Governor Gilmore's briefing books. Only a small number of documents in this series were actually created by the policy office and very few of them are restricted by executive privilege.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Secretary of Administration
II. Secretary of Commerce and Trade
III. Secretary of Education
IV. Secretary of Finance
V. Secretary of Health and Human Resources
VI. Secretary of Natural Resources
VII. Secretary of Public Safety
VIII. Secretary of Technology
IX. Secretary of Transportation
X. Miscellaneous
XI. Records of Lee E. Goodman
XII. Policy Analysis
Contents List
- I. Secretary of Administration, 1998-2001., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-1A)
  The Secretary of Administration series is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by state agency. Agencies include: Commission on Local Government, Department of Employee Relations Counselors, Department of General Services, and Department of Human Resource Management.
  Notable files include: 1998 State Song Competition entries (including cassette records); Executive Mansion Renovation records (1998-2000) including blueprints and CDs of photographs of renovation work; videotapes of Governor Gilmore's state employee town hall meetings in September 1998; and final results of the Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees (12 December 1998).
  - Commission on Local Government - 1998 State Song Competition includes cassette recording and Fact Sheet (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Department of Employee Relations Counselors - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services - eVA Brochure and Presentations (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, 5 CDs (Record Documents, Power Point Presentation and 3cds of photographs of renovation work) - for print outs of Record Documents see Box 1A (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, 5 CDs ( photographs of renovation work) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Department of General Services - Blueprints of Restoration of the Executive Mansion (Phase 1 - West Gate and North Addition; Phase 2 - Carriage House Renovation; Phase 3 - Cottage Renovation; Phase 4 - Mansion Restoration; and Security Center) (All oversize - see Map Case 24, Drawer 14) (RESTRICTED) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Government Performance Project: State Government Survey, Human Resources Management Section, 2000 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Report: Commission on Reform of the Classified Compensation Plan, 2000 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Videotapes: Compensation Reform (6 September 2000) and Virginia Performance Management Program (2000 November 7) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Copies of Executive Orders: Executive Order 2 (1998) Equal Opportunity; Executive Order 26 (1998) Maintaining a Lean, Efficient and Effective Government Work Force; Executive Order 37 (1999) Workplace Safety and Health; Executive Order 44 (1999) Commonwealth of Virginia Campaign; Executive Order 52 (1999) Workplace Safety and Health; Executive Order 53 (1999) Review of Virginia's Compliance with the Fair Labor Standards Act; Executive Order 65 (2000) Implementing Electronic Government in the Commonwealth of Virginia and Executive Order 73 (2001) Expand the Use of the Internet for the Commonwealth's Recruitment and Position Advertising (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Commonwealth of Virginia Campaign information and photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - 1998-2001 issues of Commonwealth Currents (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - 2000-2001 Virginia Public Service Week Information (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Workers' Compensation Program notebook (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - U.S. Savings Bonds Promotional Video (2001 February) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Videotapes of "Governor Jim Gilmore State Employee Town Hall Meetings" Roanoke, 23 September 1998 and Norfolk, 1998 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Videotapes of "Governor Jim Gilmore State Employee Town Hall Meetings" Annandale, 24 September 1998 and Richmond, 1998 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Town Hall Meeting photographs (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 1, Table 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 1, Table 2 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 1, Table 3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 1, Table 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 2, Table 5 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 2, Table 6 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 2, Table 7 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 2, Table 8 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 2, Table 9 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Final Data Tables (12 December 1998), Volume 2, Table 10 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Department of Human Resource Management - Governor's Survey of Virginia State Employees, Governor's Briefing, 1999 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Secretary of Administration - E-mail messages concerning the above material, 2001 August (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, Record Project Manual, Phase 1: West Gate and North Addition, 16 October 1998 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, Record Project Manual, Phase 2: Carriage House, March 1999 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, Record Specifications, Phase 3: Cottage Renovation, 31 March 1999 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, Record Project Manual, Phase 4: Mansion Renovation, 29 March 1999 (part one) (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services - Executive Mansion Renovation, Record Project Manual, Phase 4: Mansion Renovation, 29 March 1999 (part two) (Box 1A, Folder 5)
- Series II. Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 1998-2001., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 2-3)
  The Secretary of Commerce and Trade series is housed in 2 boxes. Notable files include: Governor's Opportunity Fund Projects containing recommendations from Secretary of Commerce and Trade (arranged alphabetically); Governor Gilmore's foreign trade mission itineraries and briefing books for trips to Germany (1998 April 26 to May 1), South America (1999 May 22 to June 5), Japan, Korea, Taiwan and Hong Kong (2000 June 3 to June 14) and Germany, United Kingdom and Ireland (2001 April 21 to May 4); and briefing material for Tobacco Workers Unity Summit in Richmond (1998 June 11); briefing materials for the Southern States Energy Board meeting in Memphis, Tennessee (1998 September 12-13) and Tobacco Workers Unity Summit in Richmond (1998 June 11).
  - The Virginia Strategy: Prosperity into the New Century - correspondence and working papers, 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Virginia Strategy: Prosperity into the New Century - Briefing material for Governor's Advisory Committee Meeting, 1998 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Virginia Strategy: Prosperity into the New Century - Final document and briefing memorandums concerning Virginia Strategy announcements in December 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Workforce Strategy - Virginia Workforce Council Briefing Book, 1999 August 12 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Workforce Strategy - Correspondence and working papers, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Workforce Strategy - Correspondence and working papers, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Astrolink International LLC/Prince William County - Alfa Laval Corporation/Henrico County (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Altec Industries, Inc./Botetourt County - Carlisle Motion Control Industries, Inc./Town of South Hill (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Carmar Group, Inc./Shenandoah County - Ferguson Enterprises/City of Newport News (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Fidelity Holdings, Inc./Henrico County - HP Hood/Frederick County (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Hewlett Packard/Henrico County - Kraft Foods, Inc./Frederick County (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - LKM Industries, Inc./Alleghany County - Novozymes Biologicals, Inc./Roanoke County (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Oceana Sensors Technologies/City of Virginia Beach - Sara Lee Coffee and Tea Company/City of Suffolk (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Sherwood Brands, Inc./Charlotte County - Unique Industries, Inc./Pittsylvania County (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Governor's Opportunity Fund: Projects, 1998-2001 - Universal Companies/Washington County - Zim-American Israeli Shipping Company/City of Norfolk (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Investment Partnership: Grants, 2000-2001 - B.I. Chemicals, Inc. - WorldCom UUNET Campus Expansion (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Trade Mission Itineraries - Germany, 1998 April 26 to 1998 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Trade Mission Itineraries - South America, 1999 May 22 to 1999 June 5 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Trade Mission Itineraries - Japan, Korea, Taiwan and Hong Kong, 2000 June 3 to 2000 June 14 (copy one) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Trade Mission Itineraries - Japan, Korea, Taiwan and Hong Kong, 2000 June 3 to 2000 June 14 (copy two) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Trade Mission Itineraries - Japan, Korea, Taiwan and Hong Kong, 2000 June 3 to 2000 June 14 (copy three) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Trade Mission - Japan, Korea, Taiwan and Hong Kong, Country Briefings (2000 June 3 to 2000 June 14) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Trade Mission - Japan, Korea, Taiwan and Hong Kong, Notes (unidentified) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Trade Mission Itineraries - Germany, United Kingdom and Ireland, 2001 April 21 to 2001 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Annual Incentives Reports - Report on Business Incentives: 1997-1998 (1998 November 4) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Incentives Reports - Report on Business Incentives: 1998-1999 (1999 November 4) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Incentives Reports - Report on Business Incentives: 1999-2000 (2000 November 4) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Incentives Reports - Report on Business Incentives: 2000-2001 (2001 November 4) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Advanced Shipbuilding and Carrier Integration Center - Files, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Disaster Recovery Task Force - Final Report (City of Franklin) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Commerce Quarterly Newsletter - 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bayview Report - Summary, ca. 1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Select Agency Annual Reports - Department of Business Assistance, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Select Agency Annual Reports - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Select Agency Annual Reports - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Select Agency Annual Reports - Virginia Small Business Development Center Network, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Economic Development Announcements - List of Projects, 1998 January 17 to 2001 December 14 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Regional Competitiveness Project - List of Projects, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Community Development Block Grants - List of Projects, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Community Development Block Grants - 1998 Governor's Briefing Package (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Industrial Site Development Fund Grants - List of Grants, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Enterprise Zone Designations - List of Designations, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Southern States Energy Board - 38th Annual Meeting, Doardo, Puerto Rico, 1998 August 30 to 1998 September 1, Briefing Materials (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Southern States Energy Board - 39th Annual Meeting, Memphis, Tennessee, 1998 September 12 to 1998 September 13, Briefing Materials (first copy) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Southern States Energy Board - 39th Annual Meeting, Memphis, Tennessee, 1998 September 12 to 1998 September 13, Briefing Materials (second copy) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Southern States Energy Board - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Utility Restructuring in Virginia - Updated Report, 2001 December 17 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Tobacco Workers Unity Summit - Richmond, Virginia, 1998 June 11, Briefing Materials (part one) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Tobacco Workers Unity Summit - Richmond, Virginia, 1998 June 11, Briefing Materials (part two) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Tobacco Workers Unity Summit - Richmond, Virginia, 1998 June 11, Event Preparation Materials of Lila Young, Deputy Press Secretary (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Tobacco Workers Unity Summit - Richmond, Virginia, 1998 June 11, Media Kit (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Tobacco Workers Unity Summit - Richmond, Virginia, 1998 June 11, Correspondence and Report (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous - Appalachian Regional Commission, Quorum Meeting, Washington, D.C., 2000 February 27, Briefing Materials (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous - 1998 Regional Economic Outlook Conference, Richmond, Virginia, 1998 January 28, Briefing Materials (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous - Virginia Baseball Stadium Authority, Briefing Material for Governor James S. Gilmore, III, 2001 August 17 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous - Memo to John A. Mahone, Governor Gilmore's Deputy Chief of Staff from Joshua N. Lief, Deputy Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 2001 August 31 - outlining documents Governor may wish to retain (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous - Press Release and Talking Points for Presentation of National Emergency Grant, 2001 November 1 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Series III. Secretary of Education, 1998-2001., Extent: 20 folders. (Box 4)
  The Secretary of Education series is housed in 20 folders. Notable files include: final report of The Governor's Commission on Local School Construction, 31 December 1998; Interim Report of the Governor's Blue Ribbon Commission on Higher Education, 31 December 1998; and remarks prepared for Governor Gilmore on Bond Package for Virginia's Colleges and Universities, 13 December 2001.
  - 1999 Budget Amendments on Higher Education - Briefing Material for Governor's Tour to Announce Major Initiatives, 1998 December 14-15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Issues Briefing: 2000 Education Initiatives, Presentation to Governor James S. Gilmore, III by Secretary of Education Wilbert Bryant, 1999 August 18 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Building Virginia's Future: A Time for All Virginians" - Briefing on 2000-2002 Budget Priorities from Secretary of Education Wilbert Bryant, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Governor's Commission on Local School Construction - Final Report, 1998 December 31 (copy one) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Governor's Commission on Local School Construction - Final Report, 1998 December 31 (copy two) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Governor's Commission on Local School Construction - Final Report, 1998 December 31 (copy three) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Governor's Commission on Local School Construction - Final Report, 1998 December 31 (copy four) (Box 4, Folder 6a)
  - Teacher Salary Study Briefing from the Secretary of Education, 1999 November 5 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - New Century Scholars - Proposal Prepared for Governor James S. Gilmore, III by the Office of the Secretary of Education, 1999 November 19 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - SOL/SOA Working Group - Briefing Material, 2000 May 30 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - History and Social Science Standards of Learning Teacher Resource Guide, Department of Education, 1999 (part one) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - History and Social Science Standards of Learning Teacher Resource Guide, Department of Education, 1999 (part two) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - History and Social Science Standards of Learning Teacher Resource Guide, Department of Education, 1999 (part three) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - History and Social Science Standards of Learning Teacher Resource Guide, Department of Education, 1999 (part four) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Prepaid Education Program - 1998 Actuarial Report (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Governor's Academic Challenge - Press Release and Talking Points, 2000 October 26 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Accord Between the Commonwealth of Virginia and United States Department of Education, Office for Civil Rights, 2001 November (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Celebration 2007 Briefing, 1998 August 3 (Box 4, Folder 16a)
  - Interim Report of the Governor's Blue Ribbon Commission on Higher Education, 1998 December 31 (Box 4, Folder 16b)
  - Remarks as Prepared for Governor Jim Gilmore - Bond Packaged for Virginia's Colleges and Universities, 2001 December 13 (Box 4, Folder 16c)
- IV. Secretary of Finance, 1999-2000., Extent: 7 folders. (Box 4)
  The Secretary of Finance series is housed in 7 folders. Notable files include: a copy of Productivity Savings Plans: A Briefing for Governor Gilmore, 2000 September 19 that contains state agency strategies for general fund productivity savings. This series does not contain budgetary information per section 1D of the LVA-Gilmore agreement.
  - Government Performance Project 2000: Virginia's Response, 2000 May (part one) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Government Performance Project 2000: Virginia's Response, 2000 May (part two) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Government Performance Project 2000: Virginia's Response, 2000 May (CD-ROM) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Government Performance Project 2000: Virginia's Response - A Presentation by Ronald L. Tillett, Secretary of Finance, 2000 May 24 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Actual Fiscal Year 2000 Revenues and the State of the Virginia Economy - A Presentation to the Senate Finance, House Finance and House Appropriations Committees by Ronald L. Tillett, Secretary of Finance, 2000 August 21 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Productivity Savings Plans: A Briefing for Governor Gilmore, 2000 September 19 (authored by the Department of Planning and Budget) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Federal Retiree Settlement Plan ("Harper Payments") - memorandum concerning acceleration of Harper Payment, 1999 July-August (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Series V. Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 1998-2001., Extent: 27 folders. (Box 4-5)
  The Secretary of Health and Human Resources series is housed in 27 folders. Notable files include: briefing materials on Family Access to Medical Insurance Security plan (FAMIS), 1999; Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Service, Mental Health Reform Plan, 1998 and 2000; and copies of court records concerning Hugh Finn, a Prince William County resident, whose wife, Michelle Finn, removed him from life support in 1998. Governor Gilmore intervened in the case to prevent this action.
  - State Children's Health Insurance Program, ca. 1998 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Children's Medical Security Insurance Plan (CMSIP), Department of Social Services, Marketing Communications Review, 1999 April 28 (Box 4, Folder 25)